So here's the most important economic fact of our time.
إليكم الحقيقة الاقتصادية الأكثر أهمية في عصرنا.
We are living in an age of surging income inequality,
إننا نعيش في عصر من عدم المساواة في الدخل المتزايد،
particularly between those at the very top
لا سيما بين أولئك في القمة
and everyone else.
وأي شخص آخر.
This shift is the most striking in the U.S. and in the U.K.,
هذا التحول هو الأكثر لفتاً في الولايات المتحدة و المملكة المتحدة،
but it's a global phenomenon.
بل إنها ظاهرة عالمية.
It's happening in communist China,
هذا يحدث في الصين الشيوعية،
in formerly communist Russia,
في روسيا الشيوعية سابقاً،
it's happening in India, in my own native Canada.
إنه يحدث في الهند، في بلدي الأصلي كندا.
We're even seeing it in cozy social democracies
نحن نراها حتى في الديمقراطيات الاجتماعية الحميمة
like Sweden, Finland and Germany.
مثل السويد، فنلندا وألمانيا.
Let me give you a few numbers to place what's happening.
دعوني أقدم لكم بعض الأرقام لتوضيح ما يحدث.
In the 1970s, the One Percent
في السبعينات، واحد بالمائة
accounted for about 10 percent of the national income
يمتلكون نحو 10 في المائة من الدخل القومي
in the United States.
في الولايات المتحدة.
Today, their share has more than doubled
اليوم، نصيبهم يرتفع إلى أكثر من الضعف
to above 20 percent.
إلى أكثر من 20 في المئة.
But what's even more striking
ولكن الأكثر إثارة للانتباه
is what's happening at the very tippy top
هو ما يحدث في أعلى القمة
of the income distribution.
من توزيع الدخل.
The 0.1 percent in the U.S.
0.1 بالمئة في الولايات المتحدة
today account for more than eight percent
اليوم يستأثرون بأكثر من 8 في المئة
of the national income.
من الدخل القومي.
They are where the One Percent was 30 years ago.
لقد كانوا يمثلون واحد بالمائة قبل 30 عاماً.
Let me give you another number to put that in perspective,
سأعطيكم رقم آخر لوضع الأمور في نصابها،
and this is a figure that was calculated in 2005
وهذا الرقم المحسوب في عام 2005
by Robert Reich,
بواسطة [روبرت رايخ]،
the Secretary of Labor in the Clinton administration.
وزير العمل في إدارة كلينتون.
Reich took the wealth of two admittedly very rich men,
رايخ حسب ثروة أغنى رجلين،
Bill Gates and Warren Buffett,
[بيل غيتس] و [وارن بافيت]،
and he found that it was equivalent to the wealth
ووجد أنها تساوي ثروة
of the bottom 40 percent of the U.S. population,
40 في المئة من سكان الولايات المتحدة،
120 million people.
120 مليون شخص.
Now, as it happens,
الآن، وكما يحدث،
Warren Buffett is not only himself a plutocrat,
[وارن بافيت] ليس فقط الوحيد البلوتوقراطي (شخص متنفذ بسبب ثروته)،
he is one of the most astute observers of that phenomenon,
هو واحد من أكثر المراقبين المخضرمين لهذه الظاهرة،
and he has his own favorite number.
وكان لديه رقمه المفضل.
Buffett likes to point out that in 1992,
[بافيت] يشير إلى ذلك في عام 1992،
the combined wealth of the people
إجمالي ثروة الأشخاص
on the Forbes 400 list --
على قائمة "فوربس 400" --
and this is the list of the 400 richest Americans --
والقائمة هذه لأغنى 400 أمريكي --
was 300 billion dollars.
كانت 300 مليار دولار.
Just think about it.
فكروا في الأمر.
You didn't even need to be a billionaire
أنت لست بحاجة إلى أن تكون ملياردير
to get on that list in 1992.
لتكون في هذه القائمة عام 1992.
Well, today, that figure has more than quintupled
حسناً، اليوم، هذا الرقم تضاعف إلى أكثر من خمسة أضعاف
to 1.7 trillion,
إلى 1.7 تريليون،
and I probably don't need to tell you
وأنا على الأرجح لست بحاجة لأقول لكم
that we haven't seen anything similar happen
أننا لم نر أي شيء مماثل يحدث
to the middle class,
للطبقة الوسطى،
whose wealth has stagnated if not actually decreased.
الذين ظلت ثروتهم راكدة إذا لم تنخفض أصلاً.
So we're living in the age of the global plutocracy,
لذا نحن نعيش في عصر النخبة الثرية العالمية،
but we've been slow to notice it.
ولكن كنّا متأخرين في ملاحظة ذلك.
One of the reasons, I think,
أحد الأسباب، أعتقد،
is a sort of boiled frog phenomenon.
هو نوع من ظاهرة (الضفدع المغلي).
Changes which are slow and gradual
التغيرات البطيئة والتدريجية
can be hard to notice
سيكون من الصعب ملاحظتها
even if their ultimate impact is quite dramatic.
حتى لو كان تأثيرها النهائي كبيرًا جدا.
Think about what happened, after all, to the poor frog.
فكروا ماذا حدث، بعد كل شيء، للضفدع المسكين.
But I think there's something else going on.
ولكن أعتقد أن شيئاً ما يحدث.
Talking about income inequality,
الحديث عن عدم المساواة في الدخل،
even if you're not on the Forbes 400 list,
حتى لو لم تكن على قائمة "فوربس 400"،
can make us feel uncomfortable.
يمكن أن يجعلنا نشعر بعدم الارتياح.
It feels less positive, less optimistic,
إنه شعور أقل إيجابية، أقل تفاؤلا،
to talk about how the pie is sliced
للحديث عن كيف قسمت الكعكة
than to think about how to make the pie bigger.
بدلاً من التفكير في كيفية جعل الكعكة أكبر.
And if you do happen to be on the Forbes 400 list,
وإذا كنتم على قائمة "فوربس 400"،
talking about income distribution,
الحديث عن توزيع الدخل،
and inevitably its cousin, income redistribution,
ولامحالة قرينها، إعادة توزيع الدخل،
can be downright threatening.
قد يكون مصدر تهديد بشكل صريح.
So we're living in the age of surging income inequality,
لذا نحن نعيش في عصر من عدم المساواة في الدخل المتزايد،
especially at the top.
خاصةً في أعلى الهرم.
What's driving it, and what can we do about it?
ما الذي يحرك ذلك، وماذا يمكننا أن نفعل حياله؟
One set of causes is political:
أحد مجموعة الأسباب هي سياسية:
lower taxes, deregulation, particularly of financial services,
خفض الضرائب، رفع القيود، خاصة الخدمات المالية،
privatization, weaker legal protections for trade unions,
الخصخصة، ضعف الحماية القانونية لنقابات العمّال،
all of these have contributed
كل هذا قد ساهم
to more and more income going to the very, very top.
في انتقال الدخل إلى أعلى القمة أكثر وأكثر.
A lot of these political factors can be broadly lumped
الكثير من هذه العوامل السياسية يمكن جمعها بشكل عام
under the category of "crony capitalism,"
تحت فئة "المحسوبية الرأسمالية"،
political changes that benefit a group
التغيرات السياسية التي تعود بالنفع على مجموعة
of well-connected insiders
من المطلعين المرتبطين ارتباطا وثيقا
but don't actually do much good for the rest of us.
ولكن في الواقع لا تعود بالنفع على بقيتنا.
In practice, getting rid of crony capitalism
عملياً، التخلص من رأسمالية المحسوبية
is incredibly difficult.
صعب للغاية.
Think of all the years reformers of various stripes
فكروا في كل سنوات الإصلاحيين من مختلف المشارب
have tried to get rid of corruption in Russia, for instance,
وقد حاولوا التخلص من الفساد في روسيا، مثلاً،
or how hard it is to re-regulate the banks
أو مدى صعوبة إعادة تنظيم البنوك
even after the most profound financial crisis
حتى بعد الأزمة المالية الأكثر عمقاً
since the Great Depression,
منذ الكساد العظيم،
or even how difficult it is to get the big multinational companies,
أو حتى مدى صعوبة جعل الشركات الكبرى متعددة الجنسيات،
including those whose motto might be "don't do evil,"
بما في ذلك تلك التي قد يكون شعارها "لا تفعل الشر"
to pay taxes at a rate even approaching that
تدفع الضرائب بمعدّل يقترب حتى
paid by the middle class.
من المعدّل الذي تدفعه الطبقة المتوسطة.
But while getting rid of crony capitalism in practice
ولكن في حين أن التخلص من رأسمالية المحسوبية عمليا
is really, really hard,
صعب للغاية،
at least intellectually, it's an easy problem.
على الأقل فكرياً، ستكون مشكلة سهلة.
After all, no one is actually in favor of crony capitalism.
على كلٍّ، لا أحد في الواقع يؤيد رأسمالية المحسوبية.
Indeed, this is one of those rare issues
في الواقع، هذه واحدة من القضايا النادرة
that unites the left and the right.
التي توحّد اليسار واليمين.
A critique of crony capitalism is as central
نقد رأسمالية المحسوبية أمر أساسي
to the Tea Party as it is to Occupy Wall Street.
بالنسبة لحزب الشاي كما هو الحال في احتلال وول ستريت.
But if crony capitalism is, intellectually at least,
ولكن إذا كانت الرأسمالية المحسوبية، فكرياً على الأقل،
the easy part of the problem,
الجزء السهل من المشكلة،
things get trickier when you look at the economic drivers
الامور تصبح أكثر تعقيدا عندما تنظر إلى الدوافع الاقتصادية
of surging income inequality.
لعدم المساواة في الدخل المتنامي.
In and of themselves, these aren't too mysterious.
بحد ذاتها، هي ليست غامضة جدا.
Globalization and the technology revolution,
العولمة وثورة التكنولوجيا،
the twin economic transformations
التحولات الاقتصادية المزدوجة
which are changing our lives
التي تغير حياتنا
and transforming the global economy,
وتحوِّل الاقتصاد العالمي،
are also powering the rise of the super-rich.
هي أيضا المحرّك لصعود الثراء الفاحش.
Just think about it.
فكروا في الأمر.
For the first time in history,
لأول مرة في التاريخ،
if you are an energetic entrepreneur
إذا كنت رائد أعمال ذكي
with a brilliant new idea
مع فكرة جديدة رائعة
or a fantastic new product,
أو منتج جديد رائع،
you have almost instant, almost frictionless access
لديك إمكانية الوصول الفوري، الوصول عديم الاحتكاك
to a global market of more than a billion people.
إلى السوق العالمية لأكثر من مليار شخص.
As a result, if you are very, very smart
كنتيجة لذلك، إذا كنت ذكي جدًا جدًا
and very, very lucky,
ومحظوظ، جدًا جدًا،
you can get very, very rich
يمكنك أن تكون غني جدًا جدًا
very, very quickly.
بسرعة شديدة جدًا.
The latest poster boy for this phenomenon
أحدث مثال على هذه الظاهرة
is David Karp.
هو ديفيد كارب.
The 26-year-old founder of Tumblr
مؤسس "تمبلر" البالغ من العمر 26 سنة
recently sold his company to Yahoo
باع شركته مؤخرًا لـ "ياهو"
for 1.1 billion dollars.
مقابل 1.1 مليار دولار.
Think about that for a minute:
فكروا في ذلك لبرهة:
1.1 billion dollars, 26 years old.
1.1 مليار دولار، بعمر 26 سنة.
It's easiest to see how the technology revolution
من السهل جدا رؤية كيف أن ثورة التكنولوجيا
and globalization are creating this sort of superstar effect
والعولمة يمكنها إيجاد مثل هذا النوع من تأثير النجوم
in highly visible fields,
في المجالات المعروفة،
like sports and entertainment.
مثل الرياضة والترفيه.
We can all watch how a fantastic athlete
يمكننا جميعاً رؤية الرياضيين الرائعين
or a fantastic performer can today leverage his or her skills
أو الموهوبين الرائعين كيف أن بإمكانهم اليوم توسيع مهاراتهم
across the global economy as never before.
عبر الاقتصاد العالمي كما لم يحدث من قبل.
But today, that superstar effect
لكن اليوم، تأثير ذلك النجم
is happening across the entire economy.
يحدث في مختلف قطاعات الاقتصاد بأكمله.
We have superstar technologists.
لدينا نجوم التكنولوجيا.
We have superstar bankers.
لدينا النجوم المصرفيين.
We have superstar lawyers and superstar architects.
لدينا محامين نجوم ومعماريين نجوم.
There are superstar cooks
هناك طهاة نجوم
and superstar farmers.
ومزارعين نجوم.
There are even, and this is my personal favorite example,
بل هناك، و هذا مثالي المفضل،
superstar dentists,
أطبّاء أسنان نجوم،
the most dazzling exemplar of whom
أوضح مثال على ذلك
is Bernard Touati, the Frenchman who ministers
هو برنارد تواتي الفرنسي الذي يهتم
to the smiles of fellow superstars
لتلك الابتسامة من نظرائه
like Russian oligarch Roman Abramovich
مثل الروسي الأ ليغاركي رومان ابراموفيتش
or European-born American fashion designer
أو مصممة الأزياء الأوروبية المولد- الأميركية
Diane von Furstenberg.
ديان فون فورستنبرغ‏.
But while it's pretty easy to see how globalization
ولكن في حين أنه من السهل جدًا رؤية العولمة
and the technology revolution
وثورة التكنولوجيا
are creating this global plutocracy,
تنتج هذه البلوتوقراطية(النخبة الثرية) العالمية،
what's a lot harder is figuring out what to think about it.
من الصعب جدًا معرفة كيف نفكر حيالها.
And that's because,
وذلك بسبب،
in contrast with crony capitalism,
أنه على النقيض من الرأسمالية المحسوبية،
so much of what globalization and the technology revolution
الكثير جدًا مما فعلته العولمة و ثورة التكنولوجيا
have done is highly positive.
كان إيجابياً للغاية.
Let's start with technology.
لنبدأ مع التكنولوجيا.
I love the Internet. I love my mobile devices.
أنا أحب الإنترنت. أحب أجهزتي النقالة.
I love the fact that they mean that
أحب هذه الحقيقة التي تعني
whoever chooses to will be able to watch this talk
أياً كان سيكون قادراً على مشاهدة هذه المحادثة
far beyond this auditorium.
بعيداً عن هذه القاعة.
I'm even more of a fan of globalization.
أنا حتى من المعجبين كثيرًا بالعولمة.
This is the transformation
هذا هو التحول
which has lifted hundreds of millions
الذي نقل مئات الملايين
of the world's poorest people out of poverty
من أشد الناس فقرا في العالم للخروج من الفقر
and into the middle class,
إلى الطبقة الوسطى،
and if you happen to live in the rich part of the world,
إذا كنت تعيش في الجزء الغني من العالم،
it's made many new products affordable --
الذي يصنع منتجات عديدة جديدة بأسعار معقولة --
who do you think built your iPhone? —
من بظنّكم صنع جهازكم الآيفون؟
and things that we've relied on for a long time much cheaper.
والأشياء التي اعتمدنا عليها لمدة طويلة أرخص بكثير.
Think of your dishwasher or your t-shirt.
فكّروا في غسالة صحونكم أو قميصكم.
So what's not to like?
لذا، مالذي لانحبه؟
Well, a few things.
حسناً، بضعة أشياء.
One of the things that worries me
أحد الأشياء التي تقلقني
is how easily what you might call meritocratic plutocracy
هو مدى سهولة ما يمكن أن تسموه النخبة الثرية الكفؤة
can become crony plutocracy.
يمكن أن تصبح نخبة ثرية قائمة على المحسوبية.
Imagine you're a brilliant entrepreneur
تخيل أنك رائد أعمال بارع
who has successfully sold that idea or that product
الذي باع بنجاح تلك الفكرة أو ذلك المنتج
to the global billions
للمليارات حول العالم
and become a billionaire in the process.
وتصبح بالتالي مليارديراً.
It gets tempting at that point
يصبح الأمر مغرياً في تلك المرحلة
to use your economic nous
لاستخدام معرفتك الاقتصادية
to manipulate the rules of the global political economy
للتلاعب في قواعد الاقتصاد السياسي العالمي
in your own favor.
لمصلحتك.
And that's no mere hypothetical example.
وهذا ليس مجرد مثال افتراضي.
Think about Amazon, Apple, Google, Starbucks.
فكّروا في "أمازون"، "أبل"، "جوجل"، "ستاربكس".
These are among the world's most admired,
هذه من بين الأكثر إثارة للاعجاب في العالم،
most beloved, most innovative companies.
شركات أكثر احتراماً، أكثر ابتكاراً.
They also happen to be particularly adept
هم بارعون أيضاً
at working the international tax system
في عمل النظام الضريبي الدولي
so as to lower their tax bill very, very significantly.
بغية خفض فاتورة ضرائبهم، بشكل ملحوظ.
And why stop at just playing the global political
ولماذا التوقف عند مجرد اللعب بالنظام السياسي
and economic system as it exists
والاقتصادي العالمي كما هو قائم
to your own maximum advantage?
إلى الحد الأقصى لمصلحتك الخاصة؟
Once you have the tremendous economic power
بمجرد حصولك على القوة الاقتصادية الهائلة
that we're seeing at the very, very top of the income distribution
التي نراها في أعلى القمة لتوزيع الدخل
and the political power that inevitably entails,
والقوة السياسية التي تنطوي عليها حتمًا،
it becomes tempting as well
يصبح من المغري كذلك
to start trying to change the rules of the game
البدء بمحاولة تغيير قواعد اللعبة
in your own favor.
في صالحك.
Again, this is no mere hypothetical.
مرة أخرى، هذا ليس مجرد فرضية.
It's what the Russian oligarchs did
هذا مافعلته الأقلية الروسية
in creating the sale-of-the-century privatization
في إنشاء "بيعة القرن" لخصخصة
of Russia's natural resources.
موارد روسيا الطبيعية.
It's one way of describing what happened
إنها طريقة واحدة لوصف ماحدث
with deregulation of the financial services
مع رفع القيود عن الخدمات المالية
in the U.S. and the U.K.
في الولايات المتحدة و المملكة المتحدة.
A second thing that worries me
الشيء الثاني الذي يقلقني
is how easily meritocratic plutocracy
هو تحول النخبة الثرية الكفؤة
can become aristocracy.
بسهولة إلى أرستقراطية (طبقة النبلاء).
One way of describing the plutocrats
طريقة واحدة لوصف البلوتوقراطيين (الأثرياء المتنفذين)
is as alpha geeks,
أنهم عباقرة مهووسين،
and they are people who are acutely aware
وهم الناس الذين يدركون تمامًا
of how important highly sophisticated
مدى أهمية التحليل المتطور جدًا
analytical and quantitative skills are in today's economy.
والمهارات الكمية في اقتصاد اليوم.
That's why they are spending
لهذا السبب ينفقون
unprecedented time and resources
الوقت والموارد بشكل غير مسبوق
educating their own children.
لتعليم أطفالهم.
The middle class is spending more on schooling too,
الطبقة الوسطى أيضاً ينفقون الكثير في التعليم،
but in the global educational arms race
ولكن في سباق التسلح بالعلم
that starts at nursery school
الذي يبدأ في الحضانة
and ends at Harvard, Stanford or MIT,
وينتهي في هارفارد، ستانفودر، أو معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا،
the 99 percent is increasingly outgunned
99 بالمئة يتفوقون بشكل متزايد
by the One Percent.
بنسبة 1 في المائة.
The result is something that economists Alan Krueger
والنتيجة هي ما يسميه الاقتصاديين آلان كروجر
and Miles Corak call the Great Gatsby Curve.
ومايلز كورك بـ "منحنى جاتسبي العظيم".
As income inequality increases,
بينما يزداد عدم المساواة في الدخل،
social mobility decreases.
يقل الحراك الاجتماعي.
The plutocracy may be a meritocracy,
البلوتوقراطية (النخبة الثرية) يمكن أن تكون ذات جدارة،
but increasingly you have to be born
ولكن أكثر فأكثر يجب أن تكون ولدت
on the top rung of the ladder to even take part in that race.
على أعلى درجة من السلّم لتشارك حتى في هذا السباق.
The third thing, and this is what worries me the most,
الشيء الثالث، وهذا ما يقلقني أكثر،
is the extent to which those same largely positive forces
هو مدى نفس تلك القوى الإيجابية إلى حد كبير
which are driving the rise of the global plutocracy
التي تقود صعود النخبة الثرية العالمية
also happen to be hollowing out the middle class
تعمل على تآكل الطبقة الوسطى في نفس الوقت
in Western industrialized economies.
في الاقتصادات الصناعية الغربية.
Let's start with technology.
لنبدأ مع التكنولوجيا.
Those same forces that are creating billionaires
نفس تلك القوى التي تصنع المليارديرات
are also devouring many traditional middle-class jobs.
تلتهم العديد من فرص العمل التقليدية للطبقة الوسطى.
When's the last time you used a travel agent?
متى آخر مرة استخدمتم وكيل السفر؟
And in contrast with the industrial revolution,
وعلى النقيض من الثورة الصناعية،
the titans of our new economy
عمالقة اقتصادنا الجديد
aren't creating that many new jobs.
لايقومون بإيجاد فرص عمل جديدة متعددة.
At its zenith, G.M. employed hundreds of thousands,
في أوجها، "جنرال موتورس". توظّف مئات الآلاف،
Facebook fewer than 10,000.
"فيس بوك" توظّف أقل من 10,000.
The same is true of globalization.
نفس الشيء ينطبق على العولمة.
For all that it is raising hundreds of millions of people
ففي حين أخرجت مئات الملايين
out of poverty in the emerging markets,
من الفقر في الأسواق الناشئة،
it's also outsourcing a lot of jobs
تقوم أيضاً بالاستعانة بالكثير من الوظائف
from the developed Western economies.
من الاقتصادات الغربية المتقدمة.
The terrifying reality is
الحقيقة المرعبة هي
that there is no economic rule
أنه لاتوجد قاعدة اقتصادية
which automatically translates
والتي تترجم تلقائياً
increased economic growth
زيادة النمو الاقتصادي
into widely shared prosperity.
على نطاق واسع من الإزدهار.
That's shown in what I consider to be
هذا يظهر في ما أعتبره
the most scary economic statistic of our time.
الإحصاءات الإقتصادية الأكثر رعباً في عصرنا.
Since the late 1990s, increases in productivity
منذ أواخر التسعينات، الزيادة في الإنتاجية
have been decoupled from increases
تنفصل عن الزيادة
in wages and employment.
في الأجور والعمالة.
That means that our countries are getting richer,
هذا يعني أن بلداننا تزداد غنى،
our companies are getting more efficient,
شركاتنا تصبح أكثر كفاءة،
but we're not creating more jobs
ولكننا لانقوم بإيجاد فرص عمل أكثر
and we're not paying people, as a whole, more.
وبشكل عام لا ندفع أكثر للناس ككل.
One scary conclusion you could draw from all of this
نتيجة واحدة مخيفة يمكنكم استخلاصها من هذا كله
is to worry about structural unemployment.
هي القلق من البطالة الهيكلية.
What worries me more is a different nightmare scenario.
ما يقلقني أكثر هو سيناريو كابوس مختلف.
After all, in a totally free labor market,
بعد كل شيء، ضمن سوق عمل حرة تماما،
we could find jobs for pretty much everyone.
يمكننا إيجاد فرص عمل للجميع الى حد كبير.
The dystopia that worries me
الواقع المرير الذي يقلقني
is a universe in which a few geniuses
هو عالم مع بضعة عباقرة
invent Google and its ilk
مثل مخترعي جوجل وأمثالها
and the rest of us are employed giving them massages.
وبقيتنا يعملون لديهم مدلِّكين.
So when I get really depressed about all of this,
لذلك عندما أشعر بالاحباط عن كل هذا،
I comfort myself in thinking about the Industrial Revolution.
أُريح نفسي بالتفكير في الثورة الصناعية.
After all, for all its grim, satanic mills,
في النهاية، لكل كآبتها، تلك المصانع الشيطانية،
it worked out pretty well, didn't it?
قد عملت بشكل رائع، أليس كذلك؟
After all, all of us here are richer, healthier, taller --
في النهاية، جميعنا أكثر ثراء، وأكثر صحة، وطول
well, there are a few exceptions —
جيد، هناك عدد قليل من الاستثناءات ـــ
and live longer than our ancestors in the early 19th century.
ونعيش لفترة أطول من أجدادنا في أوائل القرن 19.
But it's important to remember
ولكن من المهم تذكّر
that before we learned how to share the fruits
أنه قبل تعلّمنا كيفية تقاسم ثمار
of the Industrial Revolution
الثورة الصناعية
with the broad swathes of society,
مع قطاعات واسعة من المجتمع،
we had to go through two depressions,
كان علينا المرور عبر فترتين من الركود،
the Great Depression of the 1930s,
الكساد العظيم في ثلاثينيات القرن العشرين،
the Long Depression of the 1870s,
الركود الطويل في السبعينات،
two world wars, communist revolutions
حربين عالميتين، الثورات الشيوعية
in Russia and in China,
في روسيا والصين،
and an era of tremendous social
وحقبة من الاضطرابات الاجتماعية
and political upheaval in the West.
والسياسية الهائلة في الغرب.
We also, not coincidentally,
أيضاً، ليس من قبيل الصدفة،
went through an era of tremendous
مررنا بحقبة هائلة
social and political inventions.
من الابتكارات الإجتماعية والسياسية.
We created the modern welfare state.
أنشأنا دولة الرفاهية الحديثة.
We created public education.
أنشأنا التعليم العام.
We created public health care.
أنشأنا الرعاية الصحية العامة.
We created public pensions.
أنشأنا المعاشات التقاعدية العامة.
We created unions.
أنشأنا النقابات.
Today, we are living through an era
اليوم ، نحن نعيش خلال عصر
of economic transformation
التحول الاقتصادي
comparable in its scale and its scope
المماثل في حجمه و نطاقه
to the Industrial Revolution.
للثورة الصناعية.
To be sure that this new economy benefits us all
للتأكّد من أن هذا الاقتصاد الجديد يفيدنا جميعا
and not just the plutocrats,
وليس فقط الطبقة الثرية المتنفذة(البلوتوقراطية)،
we need to embark on an era
نحن بحاجة إلى الشروع بعهد
of comparably ambitious social and political change.
من التغيير الاجتماعي والسياسي الطموح نسبياً.
We need a new New Deal.
نحن بحاجة اتفاق جديد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)